Finding Aid for the Arthur Christopher Benson Papers LSC.0656
UCLA Library Special Collections
Arthur Christopher Benson papers
1900-1925
UCLA Library Special Collections
Benson, Arthur Christopher
LSC.0656
1.0 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Arthur Christopher Benson (1862-1925) published his first volume of essays in 1896. In all, he published more than seventy books, including poetry, short stories, novels, biographies, and essays. The collection consists of correspondence and literary manuscripts, an unpublished novel and a presentation copy of a book of Benson's poems.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 997093353606533
Biography
Benson was born April 24, 1862; his father was Edward White Benson, who later became Archbishop of Canterbury; entered Eton as King's scholar, 1874; went to King's College, Cambridge, 1881; returned to work at Eton, 1885-1903; published first volume of essays, 1896; produced various works, including a biography of his father, Edward White Benson (1899), The Schoolmaster (1902), Land of Hope and Glory, and Peace and Other Poems (1905); in all, published more than seventy books, including poetry, short stories, novels, biographies, and essays; became master of Magdalene College, Cambridge, 1915; died June 17, 1925 at Cambridge.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of the correspondence and literary manuscripts of Arthur Christopher Benson. Manuscript titles include: The Art of the Biographer, Biographic Studies, Loopholes, Memoir of Mary Benson, Poems, The War 1914, and Bibliography of Arthur Christopher Benson. Also includes an unpublished novel and a presentation copy of a book of Benson's poems, Le Cahier Jaune.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Correspondence, book of poetry, and typescripts.
Manuscript and typescripts of unpublished material.
General note
Derived from in-house card file.
Poets, English -- 20th century -- Archives.; Authors, English -- 20th century -- Archives; Benson, Arthur Christopher; Benson, Arthur Christopher, 1862-1925--Archives.
- Correspondence, mainly from Gordon G. Wordsworth to Arthur Christopher Benson, but with 2 letters from other people, and also copies of 3 letters from various people to Gordon Wordsworth. v.p., September 1924-February 1925.; 24 pieces. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  These letters concern the purchase of Mount Scawfell by Benson and Wordsworth for the purpose of giving it to the National Trust.
- Le Cahier Jaune; poems. Eton: Privately printed., 1892.; 99pp. 22.5cm. (Box 1)
  Presentation copy from the author to Sir Walter Durnford, Provost of King's College, Cambridge.
  With this is bound: His, The Myrtle Bough, a Vale. Eton, Spottiswoode, 1903. 70pp., and his, The Olive Bough. Eton: Spottiswoode, 1904. 31pp.
  General note
  Ex libris: C.K. Ogden.
- The Art of the Biographer. Cambridge., 1917.; 49 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections, bound. (Box 1)
  Published in Royal Society of Literature of the United Kingdom, London. Essays by diverse hands, being transactions. London, 1926. 22cm. New [i.e. 3rd] series, vol.6, pp. [139]-164.
  Read April 29th, 1925.
- Biographical studies: Issak Walton, Edward Ernest Bowen, William Collins, Evelyn Shirley Shuckburgh, Henry James, The Angel [fiction?], Matthew Arnold, Crevasse [fiction?]. Cambridge., v.d.; 8 typescripts with holograph corrections, bound in 1 vol. (Box 1)
  Apparently all unpublished.
- Letters to various persons. v.p., v.d.; 2 items. Typescript, holograph. (Box 1)
  With these: 1 letter of July 26, 1926 (typescript copy) from R.M. Welsford to Lord Charnwood, and 1 letter of August 2, 1926 (typescript copy) from Charnwood to Welsford, both regarding Arthur Christopher Benson's estate.
- Loopholes. Cambridge., 1916.; Typescript with holograph corrections, bound. (Box 1)
  These were... made into a little book called Loopholes [unpublished]...
  Title on backstrip reads Fragments 1917 (omitted from Loopholes).
- [Manuscript without title. n.p.,], n.d.; 190 leaves. 23cm. Holograph marked in pencil. (Box 2)
  A novel, apparently unpublished.
- Memoir of Mary Benson. Cambridge., 1925.; Typescript (carbon), bound. (Box 2)
  A life of the author's mother.
  Ex libris: E.F. Benson.
  Unpublished.
- Poems. [A volume of miscellaneous pieces, both poetry and prose. n.p.], v.d.; 24 typescripts, some with holograph corrections. (Box 2)
  The dates, 1904, 1909, and 1916 appear on several items.
  One item dated December 13, 1903, is printed. Poems. A.C.B. appears on the spine. Bound in boards.
- The War 1914. Cambridge., n.d.; Typescript with holograph corrections, bound. (Box 2)
  Apparently unpublished.
- Bibliography of Arthur Christopher Benson. n.p., n.d.; 25pp. 26cm. Typescript with corrections in ink. (Box 2)
  Compiler unknown.
  Included are several biographical quotations from various sources.